<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A description of the province and bay of Darian giving an full account of all it's situation, inhabitants, way and manner of living and religion, solemnities, ceremonies and product, being vastly rich with gold and silver, and various other commodities / by I.B., a well-wisher to the company who lived there seventeen years.</title>
            <author>I. B. (Isaac Blackwell)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16204737</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16204737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105068</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28304)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105068)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1088:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A description of the province and bay of Darian giving an full account of all it's situation, inhabitants, way and manner of living and religion, solemnities, ceremonies and product, being vastly rich with gold and silver, and various other commodities / by I.B., a well-wisher to the company who lived there seventeen years.</title>
                  <author>I. B. (Isaac Blackwell)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heirs and successors of Andrew Anderson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Blackwell by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Indians of South America --  Colombia.</term>
               <term>Darien Scots' Colony, 1698-1700.</term>
               <term>Panama --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105068:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105068:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Deſcription OF THE PROVINCE and BAY OF DARIAN: Giving an full Account of all it's <hi>Situation, Inhabitants,</hi> Way and Manner of <hi>Living</hi> and <hi>Religion, Solemnities, Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Product;</hi> Being vaſtly rich with Gold and Silver, and various other Commodities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> I. B. <hi>a Well-wiſher to the</hi> COMPANY <hi>who lived there Seventeen Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by the Heirs and Succeſſors of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105068:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105068:2"/>
            <head>Reader,</head>
            <p>BEing deſired by a Friend to ſet out this following De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Province and Bay of <hi>DARIAN</hi> (my Friend knowing that I lived there and thereabouts ſome years ago) What I have written is both what I have ſeen and heard in the Place, and I have not peruſed one word of Mr. <hi>Dampeir</hi> or <hi>Mr. Wafer's</hi> Books; Neither do I know what Deſcription they have given of this <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> they were both my Ship-maits near ſix years in the <hi>South-Sea:</hi> I went from <hi>Golden Iſland</hi> over the Isthumus that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parats the <hi>North-Sea</hi> from the <hi>South-Sea,</hi> and there I entered aboard of the Ship which they were then in, lying in the Bay of <hi>Panama,</hi> ſo that I never did ſee any of them in the Province of <hi>DARIAN;</hi> For their Ship came round <hi>Cap-Horn</hi> in the <hi>South-Seas,</hi> therefore if that they and I do not agree in our Deſcription, is none of my fault; for what I have written is the real Truth of what I have ſeen and heard, for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of my Countrey-men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By your much obliged Servant.</hi>
                  <hi>Iſaac Blackwell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105068:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105068:3"/>
            <head>A Deſcription OF THE PROVINCE and BAY OF DARIAN.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>DARIAN</hi> is a Province lying in the <hi>Isthmus</hi> that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats the <hi>North-Sea</hi> from the <hi>South-Sea</hi> in the Latitude of 8 Degrees and 25 Minuts. <hi>North-Latitude,</hi> The Entry of the River lyeth near 30 Miles from <hi>Darian-City,</hi> which is the Metropolitan of it's Province. The Word <hi>Darian</hi> ſignifies in the <hi>Indian</hi> Speech, a Shady, City or Town. And it was never Conquered by any in Man's Memory; It's called a ſhadowed Town, becauſe it's Situated betwixt two great Ranges of high Hills, lying on the Eaſt and Weſt, and running North and South, with a River called by it's own Name, <hi>Darian River.</hi> And it lying ſo near the Line, they are not priviledged with the Sun-ſhine, but at 12 a Clock of the Day, which is near right over their Heads at that time: And then the Reflects of the Sun from off the River and Hill-ſides, cauſes ſuch an extream Heat: But ſufferable.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Darian</hi> begins from <hi>Cap de Samblas</hi> on the Weſt, and ends at <hi>Cap de Caenu</hi> on the Eaſt; this is by the <hi>Indians</hi> own allowance, tho' other Draughts makes it three times Broader. To the North lyes off theſe Iſlands <hi>Iſle de Pinos</hi> or Iſle of <hi>Pinos,</hi> and ſome other Iſlands that lyes near to the Shoar, called Iſl. de <hi>Orr</hi> or Golden Iſland. As alſo <hi>Tortuga</hi> or Tortois Iſl. becauſe of the Plenty of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105068:4"/>theſe moſt delicate &amp; wholſome <hi>Amphibius</hi> Creatures for Man's Uſe; for they participate of Fiſh, Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, &amp; Fowl, they Swim in the Sea as a Fiſh &amp; feeds upon Graſs that growes upon Rocks, like a Bull or Cow, &amp; they lay Eggs like a Fowll &amp; that incredible Numbers, for I have taken out of an hole in the Sand 300 and oddsat a time. In ſhort it's an excellent wholſome Food any manner of way dreſſed; I would ſay more of it were it not known to all to be true, that it would exceed the bounds of thir few Sheets. There is another Iſland called <hi>Furte,</hi> which lyeth off of the Mouth of the <hi>Le-goun</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raba,</hi> which ſignifieth Safe Anchorage, and indeed ſo it may be called for 1000 Sail of Ships can Ride in it with much Freedom; There's from 5 to 10 Fathome deep Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with good white chynely ground mixed with white Coryll at the Bottom, in which there is vaſt variety of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral good wholſom Fiſhes; But eſpecially that much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired Creature called <hi>Manaty,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Sea-Cow</hi> in the <hi>Indian</hi> Speech, and many other great and ſmall Fiſhes. The Mouth of this <hi>Le-goun</hi> is about 80 Yairds over, and groweth Wider the further you Sale in it; Its in Form like a <hi>Semi-Circle.</hi> The Word <hi>Le-goun</hi> ſignifies a Lake or Loch.</p>
            <p>All this whole Province of <hi>Darian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Soile.</note> is of a good Strong and fertile Soile and very wholſome, ſtrong bodied People poſſeſſe it, which they themſelves think, that it's the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſs of the Air and Climate, that makes them ſuch well bodied Men and Women. There is good ſtore of good Water Springs which flow down from off theſe high Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Mountains in the time of their Rainy Moneths, <hi>viz.</hi> from the middle of <hi>November,</hi> to the middle or end of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary:</hi> And then all the reſt of the year is fair pleaſant and Serene Weather as can be, but Hot with all, which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons their ground generally to be ſo Fertile; but eſpecially all about the Lake or <hi>Legoun</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raba.</hi> For in the time of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105068:4"/>theſe Rains all their <hi>Savanas</hi> or <hi>Salinas, id est</hi> Meadows are ſo over flown with Dirt and Rubbiſh, which is waſhed down from the high Mountains, that when it comes to ſettle u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the low Grounds, it's like to Nilus in a manner: For what they have to Sow or Plant, they do it while the Mud is yet Soft, and in 28 days time, I have ſeen Mellons, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers and Gourds and many ſuch like Roots come to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity in the ſaid time, which I ever imputed to theſe Rains and the Reflex of the Sun off of the Water and Hill-ſides down upon the Vallies or Meadow Grounds. It's an con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Summer for all things are Green there all the year o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Trees of ſome ſort of Fruit will have upon them all atone time, Bloſſoms budded or ſet Fruit, and ſome half Ripe others wind-ſhaken, various are the Numbers of all ſorts of Fruit, Trees, and other ſtately Trees, for Food and Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; As alſo all manner of wild Fowl, eſpecially Turkies and Partriges, Turtle doves, Parats, with various other ſorts of Fowles both ſmall and great: As alſo that ſmal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſect <hi>Cuchaniel.</hi> Here groweth that famous Tree called the <hi>Cocur-nute-tree,</hi> which affords all at one time, Food, Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; all other neceſſaries fitting for Houſhold Uſe. Here groweth alſo the much talked of <hi>Cabadge-Tree,</hi> which I have meaſured when blown down with the Wind, above 100 Foot betwixt the Root above Ground, and the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Cabadge that grows upon the top of it. Here grows alſo that much eſteemed Nut called <hi>Coco-Nut</hi> of which the Chacolat is made; And here alſo groweth that Rair and moſt Fragrant and Odoriferous Apple, called <hi>Pinn-Apple,</hi> which I am ſure many of your fine Ladies would give their Silk Gown for one of them to play with a while. In ſhort, I have not now Time nor Bounds, to ſet down all the moſt excellent Species of Fruits, ſuch as <hi>Mammi</hi> and <hi>Mammi Suportas,</hi> and <hi>Guovas,</hi> &amp;c. and Roots and other Herbs, which are all very Medicinal as well as wholſome for Food to Man and Beaſt.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105068:5"/>
            <p>There is likewayes found in theſe Rivers,
<note place="margin">Gold.</note> 
               <hi>viz. Darian</hi> &amp; <hi>Sancta-Maria</hi> Rivers great plenty of Gold-duſt, which the <hi>Indians</hi> drains through ſmall Veſſels with holes in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of them, in the time of theſe great Rains. The Gold is waſhed from the Mines of <hi>Sagra</hi> and the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Carabana</hi> &amp; <hi>Guattimala:</hi> Hills in ſhort, it's a Rich Countrey with Gold; for I have been told by very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Natives of the Place, that they have laughed at their <hi>Southern</hi> Neighbours <hi>Peruvians</hi> who have boaſted of their having Houſes full of Gold; That their King's Ranſom called <hi>Atabalidas</hi> who was taken Captive by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> was no leſs offered for him than an Houſe full of Gold, and if that would not do, they would give for his Ranſom four times as much Silver; his Houſe was ſaid to be 22 foot long, 17 foot broad and 36 foot high; yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all this great boaſt of the <hi>Peruvians</hi> Gold and Silver. The People of <hi>Darian</hi> laughed at them, and told them that that quantity which they bragged of, was but like a Mouſe to an <hi>Eliphant</hi> in compariſon of the Mines of <hi>Darian,</hi> which to this hour they ſay containes in them more Gold than Earth, and I have ſeen it ſo in many places my ſelf, when that I lived in <hi>Darian</hi> a few years agoe. As alſo, I have ſeen their Horſes ſhodd with Silver Shoes and with Beaten Gold, Bridles with Precious Stones, ſett in all the reſt of the Furniture, and the Houſhold Veſſells all of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Gold. I could Write much more concerning the vaſt Riches that are there in theſe places; but I know that my Countrey-men are generally <hi>Thomaſſes,</hi> or at leaſt I am ſure that they would be content to be <hi>Thomaſſes</hi> by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in this matter.</p>
            <p>I told you before that the People of <hi>Darian</hi> are a ſtrong well proportioned People, only I forgot to tell you that they are of a Dark-yellow, or Copper-colour, having lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no Beards at all, but a ſtraight Rank long Black-hair
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105068:5"/>as Jeat, ſome of them have it to their middle, others longer, Women to their heels; They Generally go all naked, eſpecially before that they be Married, and but few of the Women kind, unleſs they are of a higher degree, that ever covers their nakedneſs, even after they are Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; and when that they do it, it's not half covered either, whither it may be imputed to be the <hi>Taylors</hi> fault that takes not a true meaſure, or the <hi>Merchants</hi> fault that begroudges enough of Cloath, I know not.</p>
            <p>The Men are allowed to take as many Wives as he can keep or maintain, and the way of their Marriage is this:
<note place="margin">Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</note> A Man cannot Mary his Siſter, or Mother, or Daughter; other degrees of Kindred they reſpect not, for the Uncles Marie with their Cuſings, the more Wives a Man hath he is eſteemed the more Worthie, Great and Rich; for when any of them offends him he diſpoſes of her and her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; if that ſhe have any to be Slaves to any who will buy them, and ſo getts other Goods by the bargain, which likes him better: But Generally all his Wives live very long contentedly together, without murmuring at others en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of their Husbands oftners than others, and after any of them is with Child, ſhe will not ly with her Husband till delivered, nor yet come near Men; But when that they are fit for Men's uſe, either Maid or Married Woman will not. When that they Marry, the Man asketh the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Friends or Neighbours if that ſhe hath any, asking if that it be their will to let ſuch a Maid or ſuch a Widow Marie or Match with him; if that ſhe ſay yea, they away they go all to his houſe, and Solemnizes the Wedding in Eating and Drinking for 3 or 4 days: But at the entry to the Houſe, the Husband gives her an ear of Corn, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to her that ſhe muſt Sow the Ground, and ſhe gives him a Lance, or els a Bow and Arrow, ſignifying that he muſt go to the Warrs and Wodes to fight and hunt for his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105068:6"/>and his Family, then to ſuch Victuals and Drink as they have, which is all ſorts of <hi>Jerkt-hogg</hi> that is Fleſhed down without Bones. As alſo, all ſorts of <hi>Barbekewd</hi> meats both of Fiſh, Fleſh and Fowl, that is to ſay, all ſorts Roſted. Then for Fruits and Roots of various ſorts, they want not plenty of them, as I told you before, and for Drinks called <hi>Muſlawhi</hi> it's made of <hi>Plantings</hi> or <hi>Bonano's,</hi> which are Roots not unlike our <hi>Carrot,</hi> only alike bigg at both ends, and a little crooked, theſe they boyle all to Maſh and Strain off the clear and drink it. They have alſo Drink which is made of <hi>Maiz, Turkie-wheat</hi> and <hi>Caſader,</hi> other-wayes called <hi>Farina de Poo,</hi> whereof is made their Meal that they bake for Bread. <hi>Farina de Poo</hi> ſignifyes Flower or Wheat of Timber, ſuch as hath been Reported long agoe to be ſawings of Trees. I could fill a whole ſheet of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with the vertues and uſes of this <hi>Caſader,</hi> but however pleaſe to accept of what you have here for the time.</p>
            <p>Before they go to ly down upon their <hi>Wild-kain-tops,</hi> which is all the Bed that they uſe, they go and waſh in the River, whereon, or near to their Houſes are commonly built, and when they are well waſhed, then they return home and lye down: Their Houſes I told you are made upon River-ſides for Cleanneſs and for Air, for they make them generally of an Hutt faſhion made of wild Kains ſet together into the Ground as cloſe as can be, and covered over with the Tops of theſe Wild-kains for Cleanlineſs, for they will not diſcharge Nature upon the Ground, if that they can help it, but run into a River where that it may be carried away with the Current: But if that they be far from a River, then they dig a Hole with a Stick in the Ground, and ſo cover it up afterwards; They are cleaner about the Doors than many of the Doors at the Croſs of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> unleſs that my Countrey-folks have mended their Manners. The Men generally labour but little in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105068:6"/>the Fields, but only the Women &amp; old Folks ſo long as they are able to go alone, the Men are imployed in Hunting and Fiſhing and Fowling, and making Inſtruments for War, ſuch as Bows and Arrows, and Lances and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>When their Wives bring furth their Children, their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands take them from the Womb, and with his Teeth byts their Navel-ſtrings off, and then flatts the Noſe of the Child, either by an Squize upon it, or by tying an flat piece of Board or Bone upon it, for they covet much to be plain-faced Gentlemen, &amp; then bores a Hole through the under Lip of it, that through time I have thought that they have had two Mouths, through which I have heard them make an ſtrange ſort of an Voice, but the proper uſe is to hang Gold or precious Stones in it; As alſo they hang a piece of Gold through the Partition of their Noſe down o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Mouth and Chin, ſo hath the Woman a great thick Ring of Gold through the ſame place of their Noſes alſo, ſo that when they go to War, they attyre all themſelves with the richeſt Things that they have, and when that they Drink they are forced to hold it up with one Finger while the other Hand is at their Mouth; They hang alſo pieces of Gold at their Hair, and the Men cover their Privies with an hollow piece of Gold which is tyed about their Body witha ſmall Weeth of a Tree, then they Paint their Legs with a certain Juice of an Herb that they call <hi>Pindo,</hi> and as I take the word to be, it ſhould ſignifie <hi>Paint,</hi> for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they do paint their Legs all over; that in a ſmall time they cannot hardly waſh it off; ſo that I have thought that they had a pair of cliver ſtrait Black boots on their Leggs at a diſtance, then they oyl all their Bodies, and marches up Man and Woman, Bag and Baggage, to the Place where their King hath appointed an Randezvouze and there pitch their Tents, until that the King pleaſes to March; ye muſt know that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105068:7"/>the Stouteſt and Taleſt Men are made likeways King, and not by Heritage, and the next Taleſt and Stouteſt are Officers under him; again, they come to the Wives and Children, in the time that they are Incamped, thoſe of the braveſt and ſtouteſt Hearts amongſt them fall a cutting and ſlaſhing of their Skine with a Fiſh-tooth which they keep for the uſe: The places that they cut are their Brows, Cheeks, Arms, Shoulder-blades, Breaſts and Thighs, and ſome their Hipps, both men and Women; I have ſeen ſo Carved with all ſorts of Birds, Fowls and Fiſhes, when their Wounds are bleeding they ſtop them full of a certain powder, that both dryes and heals theſe ſmall wounds, and alſo cauſes theſe parts of their Body to ſwell and riſe higher than other places doth, of which they are very proud, becauſe they are taken for valiant and brave Men, then when they are all well, their King Proclames a Speech in this manner, my brave and Stout men, ye'll know that our Fore-fathers were moſt abominably Murdered, and their Goods taken from them, and their Wives and Children taken captives unto ſuch a Province; Therefore it becomes you all now to prove your ſelves Brave and Stout Men, in going alongſt with me to be Revenged upon them for it; Therefore declare all your minds, upon which they ſhow their willingneſs by oyling of their Bodies again; ſo that they cannot eaſily be catched hold of, and ſo Bagg and Baggadge follow in order as afore is ſaid; and when that they met within any Bow-ſhot they all let fly together ſo long as they have Arrows to ſhoot, &amp; when all is gone they fall to Work with their Lances and wooden Halbirts Pell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell, until ſome of the ſides yeild, and then the Wives fall a Plundering of the Enemies Wives, and in the mean time the Men are ſecureing the Priſoners, and afterwards they all march Home; and when that they come through any of their Towns, the King cryes out with a loud voice, <hi>Erima,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105068:7"/>Erima, Toupina-Baults Canomi, Guaſione, Tan Tan,</hi> That is, behold what valiant actions we have done for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you theſe villanous Men that abuſed our Fore-fathers; ſhal we not Murder them, Murder them, then the People call out aloud, <hi>Zanupa, Zanupa,</hi> That is to ſay <hi>furthwith furthwith,</hi> which accordingly they do, ſome in every Town, until all be killed. The way how that they kill them, is, by tying them faſt to a Poſt, and ſo Shoots Arrows at them, by degrees, until that they ſhoot him or her through the Heart, then the women quarters them and gives their bowels to their Children to rubb themſelves all over with them, to make them the more Bloody-minded againſt their enemies, when that they come to be Men, they <hi>Barbikew</hi> their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and keeps a Feaſt in the chief Place of the Town, playing upon Flutts, that either are made of other Dead Mens-leggs, or Thigh-bones, or elſe the Bones of theſe preſent whoſe fleſh are eating at the time. Then when all this Feaſt is ended, and every Man home to his Family and Peace begins to be Proclamed over all that Province, Theſe Men that are jealous of any of their Wives that have ſtayed at Home, as many of them do, they get an order from their old Pagels or Prieſts, to bring her before the People of the Town, where ſhe is ſet upon an high place above the reſt, and then the Pagel asketh her if ſhe be guilty of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or not, if that ſhe denys, then he gives her about half a Gill of a certain Red-water, which is as bitter as any Gall, or Wormwood, and gives it her to drink: which if that ſhe be guilty, it will in a quarter of an hours time burſt her Belly and rott her Thighs; and if that ſhe be not guilty, it hurts her no more than plain Water would have done, if that ſhe had drunk as much. I would deſire that none of my Countrey Women ſhould get any of this Water ſent Home as a Propine of their own Colony in <hi>Darian,</hi> for fear it prove their Honeſty, as I have it ſeen done upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105068:8"/>them poor Heathens: It looks ſomething like to the bitter Water that we read of in the Law of Jealouſie in the Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Law.</p>
            <p>When the Children are born and laid by the Mother of it, the Father brings it a little wooden Lance and a little Bow and Arrow with a wooden little Knife and Kiſſes him if a Son, ſaying unto him, my Son, when that thou art great, thou muſt be ſtrong to revenge thy ſelf upon thy Enemies. They have divers names for their Children, ſuch as <hi>Orapoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen,</hi> that is Bow and Arrow, <hi>Sarigoy,</hi> that is four footed Beaſt, <hi>Arignan,</hi> that is an Hen, <hi>Araboton,</hi> that is an <hi>American</hi> Tree, <hi>Pindo,</hi> that is an Herb they paint withall, as ye heard before. The Mother gets a drink of <hi>Muſlawhi</hi> or two, and Crambs the <hi>Pickaninis</hi> Mouth, that is to ſay the little ones Mouth, with ſome boyled Root or other, and then gives it Suck for to waſh it down with all and takes a ſmall Weeth or Bark of a Tree, tying the Child to her back, &amp; caſts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her Shoulder, which Pape or Breaſt ſhe places that whereat the Infant may Suck at its pleaſure; and ſo ſhe goes about any Buſſineſs that ſhe has to do either about their Houſe or in the Fields, They are truly brave Nurſes, for tho' that there Children are never Swadled, yet there is none amongſt them either young or old that ever I ſaw Crooked or Deformed, which I impute to the ſtrength of the Mothers Milk, I have had Children of my own Nurſed by theſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> and they take it as a great favour done to them, to let them give Suck to our Children, which they have done many times when that I lived in <hi>America.</hi> As their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren grows up they teach them how to make Bows and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, Lances and ſuch like Tools for to fight their Enemies with all, as you have heard already the way how that they fight, and how that the uſe their Priſoners.</p>
            <p>They Hunt with ſeveral ſorts of Arrows according as they deſign their Sport, ſome ſmall and ſharp pointed with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105068:8"/>a Fiſh Tooth, others bigger and blunt at the end like to a Rammer, and that is to Stun or Stupifie certain Creatures that that they keep about their Houſe, after that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Breath again. I have ſeen them ſhoot an Arrow 50 paces even out from them, and make it ſtick in a Beaſts Head or Mans Head if in time of War. They go a Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſmall <hi>Dores</hi> or <hi>Cannous</hi> or <hi>Barkloggs,</hi> or ſometimes upon Blown &amp; dreſſed Selh's skins tyed together, with which they go oft to Sea; and ſhoots with their Arrows ſome ſorts of Fiſh, and others they ſtrick with their <hi>Harpoon Irons</hi> and ſo when they are Loaden, they come home and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers their Fiſhes to the Women, who dreſſes them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they have occaſion, and that is various ways for their own uſe, and alſo to keep to complement Strangers with all when that they come amongſt them, as I may ſelf have been, eſpecially near to the City <hi>Darian,</hi> where we had ſeveral Diſhes of the aforementioned <hi>Tortoiſſes</hi> and <hi>Manaty</hi> with ſeveral other rare Fiſhes and Fowls, which are very plenty near to the Lake or Loch or <hi>Le-goun</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſpoken with old men that have deſcribed to me a great Fowl in ſhape like the <hi>Griffen,</hi> but they are all ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht of late years; As alſo are all the Lyons, Tygers, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opards and Bears that uſed to haunt the Mountains, and in ſted of them, there is great plenty of all ſorts of Munkies, &amp; delicat Fowls as is aforementioned, which Munkies are very good Meat to them that know them, I have eaten 40 times of them, and would do it yet, before I would eat Mager or Lean-fleſh.</p>
            <p>They are generally kind to all Strangers except <hi>Spaini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> whom they hate with a perfect hatred, as they have good cauſe to do, conſidering their horrid and inhumane Murder that they committed upon theſe poor ſilly harmleſs <hi>Heathens:</hi> It's not many Years ago ſince I ſaw upon the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105068:9"/>Coaſt of <hi>Peru</hi> 100 Carcages of murdered <hi>Indians</hi> turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Mumy, tho' a long time ſince; Theſe ſandy hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys keeps their Carcages from conſuming; I call them Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cages becauſe they are lying like as many dead dryed Sheep, only they want the Wool that Sheep bear in theſe parts of the World: But I will not talk of <hi>Peru</hi> till I have fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the Hiſtory of <hi>Darian.</hi> I ſay that they are kind to Strangers, for if that they know that you are deſigned to go up the Countrey, they will carry you in Ham makers up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſhoulders with two Men one on each ſide of you, carrying Water or Wine and Fire and Tobacco, if that you have occaſion for either of them, and when that ye come to the Place where their King or chief Man liveth, ye are made welcome by him and all the reſt of his Court, by hugging of you in their Arms, and ſcratching of your Back or Shoulders with their Fingers, the which you muſt do the like to them, then you are ſet down upon a Straw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matt, or ſome ſuch like thing by the King, or next beſt Man to him, and if that you have an Interpreter to acquaint them with your Buſineſs, they will all hear him, or your ſelf if that you can ſpeak the Language, until that you have made an end, and then the King tells it to all his Court round about him, which if that it be a thing that pleaſes him, he claps his right Hand a croſs his Heart, and gives two or three Nods with his Head, which all ſignifie he likes the News or your Diſcourſe with his Heart, and ſo if that he do not like it, ſhakes his Head and looks of a ſower Countenance, and crys out aloud <hi>Zeto patae,</hi> id eſt, <hi>I am not well pleaſed;</hi> But if that he is well pleaſed, then he crys aloud <hi>Yatabala Comorada,</hi> that is, <hi>ye are welcome to him as a Friend;</hi> and ſo in confirmation of this he drinks to you, clapping his Heart firſt, and afterwards takes you by the Hand, and Drinks to you, that is a ſign that ye are as wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him as his Heart, and ſo ye drink all round in this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105068:9"/>Faſhion till it comes to the King again, and then to Victuals ye go, to ſuch as I have ſpoken of already, and the way of dreſſing of it. And farder to, to complement you with the Kindneſs, they give you either their own or their Wifes Siſter to wait upon you while that you ſtay in Countrey, which if you except of them, it is taken by them as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary piece of Favour conferred upon the Family in accepting of their Relation; ye may uſe her if that you pleaſe, which if that you do, I am ſure it muſt either be for rarities Cauſe, or elſe extream Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>But be ſure that you take her not with you when that you return either to your Store-houſe, or yet a Shipboard, by conveying her ſecretly away as ſome hath done, to the great Damage of theſe that may perhaps come into the ſame Place for Trade, as I knew it once fall out not many years ago; But that if ye leave her with them, as alſo a few Beeds or ſuch like Toyes, then beſure that they ſhall convoy you down in State, with Muſick before you, and ſome of the beſt of the Place will go at your ſide, and others holding an <hi>Subumbrera</hi> (as the <hi>Spainiards</hi> call it) over your Head, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers carrying <hi>Palm-wine</hi> and <hi>Tobacco;</hi> for fire they can make it out of a green and dry Stick by Frixation preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to you, if need require.</p>
            <p>When that ye are come home either to the Store-houſe or the Ship ye cauſe compliment thoſe that conveyed you down with Beeds, Coper or Braſs-Rings, and Whiſtles of all ſorts a few of them, and they will return you 1000 times the worth of it either in Gold or in Silver, beſides what Proviſions of <hi>Barbekewed-Fiſh</hi> and Fleſh they will ſend down to you.</p>
            <p>At your departure from them, ye muſt ſhake hands and ſcart their Back as I told you before; and then they will cry out <hi>Zata faca Balla Comerada,</hi> that is, <hi>many bold and hearty ſucceſs to you my Friend;</hi> ſo away they march home and ſhow all their Wealth they have gotten from you. If ye have given them any ſmall Looking-Glaſſes, that is two or three days Work for them to behold their beautiful Faces into, and ſometimes looking upon the back ſide of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105068:10"/>Glaſs, to ſee if the Party be there that they ſaw in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of the Glaſs.</p>
            <p>Now for their Religion, you muſt know that all the Heathens in theſe Parts, have ſome ſort of a god or other that they worſhip; either for fear of Love, <hi>viz.</hi> There is a <hi>Palm-tree</hi> which affords them Wine every day: and there is a Root that they call <hi>Api</hi> they worſhip, becauſe its good for to make Bread of. There is the Sun and Moon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they receive Light from them. Next, there is the Devil they worſhip in various Shapes, as they have told me; they ſee their <hi>Valaſa,</hi> that is, <hi>their great Prophet,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in a Mans Shape, ſometimes in a Beaſts, and other times in a Birds Shape. There is a Fiſh that they call <hi>Cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that is a <hi>Crocadoil</hi> or <hi>Allagator;</hi> and there are <hi>Snails</hi> and <hi>Serpents</hi> of all ſorts that they worſhip alſo. I could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt to 10 Sheets of Paper upon their way of Worſhip, and how often in the year, and alſo what Harm comes to them that by Chance kill either of theſe gods: but wanting time, I ſhall forbear till the next Occaſion.</p>
            <p>There is one thing I cannot omit, That I have ſeen ſome ſorts of them that can neither comprehend an Oath, nor yet a Lye; though I have demonſtrat both to them, they would tell that it is impoſſible that any thing that looks like a Man, can be guilty of either.</p>
            <p>Their way of Swearing, is either by their Fathers or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers back-ſide; or if it be a great and deep Oath, then they ſwear by their Grandfathers; and if no body will believe the Truth that they are ſaying, then they ſwear by their great Grandfathers and Mothers back-ſide. But as for Lyeing, I never could get them to comprehend it. This way of Swearing they tell me hath been ever with them: I think it looks ſomething like <hi>Abrahams</hi> making of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant put his Hand under his Thigh when he was going a Wooing of a Wife for his Son. Yet this ſort of them, are they that worſhip the Devil.</p>
            <p>They have no way of Learning amongſt any of them: their way of numbering anything, is by ſmall Stones, or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105068:10"/>pickles of great Corn; and they keep thoſe that they have compted by them, till Occaſion calls for them.</p>
            <p>Their Ages they keep, or compt by ſo many Moons; they have no Names for the Months. I have reckoned up ſo many Moons, as that hath come to 105, and 110; yea, ſome 120 years old, and brisk old Men, notwithſtanding which, I impute to the wholeſomeneſs of the Countrey of <hi>Darian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is others of them that believes the Reſurrection of the Body; becauſe I have ſeen of their Graves that have been accidentally opened; and theſe of their Friends have gone and taken all their Bones and carried them Home, and put them in a place where that they would ly ſafe: I have ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them the Reaſon of it; they would tell me that he would have occaſion for them, when he ſhould riſe to go behind the great High-hill where all the brave and ſtrong Men goe; and theſe that are not brave and ſtrong men, when they Riſe, they go to a dark Cave, and there neither hear, nor ſee the brave Singing and Dancing, that they that go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the high Hill ſee, hear and act alſo: but ſhall ſtay in that place till one <hi>Agga</hi> ſhall come and beat his Bones to pieces. <hi>Agga,</hi> that is, <hi>an evil or bad man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Phyſicians they call <hi>Paggies,</hi> plays the Rogue much with them, for they know certain Herbs and Gumms, that when they pleaſe to tell them that they are ſick in ſuch a part of their Body, that they apply a Bliſtering Plaſter to it, which immediatly bliſter their Fleſh, and as ſoon they will heal it, by applying of a certain Gumm, of which there is great Store of all ſorts, both of Herbs, Oyls and Gumms in this Province of <hi>Darian;</hi> I have ſeen the Effects of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verals of them tryed to admiration.</p>
            <p>Their Diſeaſes are generally <hi>Calentures, Fluxes</hi> and <hi>Yeas,</hi> or that we call the <hi>Clap,</hi> at which they are very dextrous, in curing in 24 Hours time, by a certain Root they give inwardly for that Effect.</p>
            <p>When they are lying on Death-bed, their Friends Dance Sing and Roar all the time Night and Day, and the ſick Perſon takes it as a great piece of Kindneſs done to him to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105068:11"/>attend him in this manner. But as ſoon as he is dead, they howl and mourn with extreme Howlings, eſpecially if he was a man of Eſteem amongſt them, or yet a brave ſtrong man. Alſo the old Women cryes out, O what a luſty and ſtrong and cunning Hunter and Fiſher this <hi>Ehu</hi> (that is man) was! Thus they continue for ſix Hours time untill he be buried, for they keep none in theſe parts longer than ſix Hours time, and they bury them in a deep Hole upright putting in above him Fowls Feathers of various Colours to deck his Lance and weapons of VVar with, when he ſhall go to the back of the Hill and Dance with the reſt of the brave men that are gone before him: Alſo they power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him ſome Palm wine and ſet a ſtaff before him, and ſome Tobacco and Pipes, then they deſire him to mind them to ſuch and ſuch as are gone before him to Dance at the back of this great Hill, and they put the Earth about him, and returns with a Lamentation, Crying out, O this ſtrong <hi>Ehu</hi> is gone! who will bring us now the Bodies of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to eat as he uſed to do; Thus they continue to mourn for a VVeeks time.</p>
            <p>Thus far I have given you a true and Real Diſcription of the Province of <hi>Darian,</hi> both as to the People and their Cuſtoms and Ceremonies; as alſo the nature of the Soil, with the Production thereof: If that it be kindly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I ſhall give you a Map of the whole Province with all the Rivers and Villages, with a fuller Diſcription than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny extant.</p>
            <p>I would have put furth a Map of <hi>Darian</hi> with it's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Places; but knowing that there are many who will not underſtand a Map, that can underſtand a Printed Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription, eſpecially of the Province where now <hi>New-Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> is ſtated in <hi>Cal donia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But knowing that ſome People are like Children, who love to play with bony Pictures; they ſhal be pleaſed within a ſmall time with a Map containing all the varities of the Place, the ſhapes of Men and Women, Beaſts and Birds, Fruits and Trees.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
